JAKE : When I was lying there in the VA hospital,
with a big hole blown through
the middle of my life,
I started having
these dreams of flying.
I was free.
Sooner or later, though,
you always have to wake up.
They can fix a spinal,
if you got the money,
but not on vet benefits,
not in this economy.
A VA check and 12 bucks
will get you a cup of coffee.
I'm what they call...
waitlisted.
WOMAN ON TV : The Bengal Tiger, extinct for
over a century is making a comeback.
These cloned tiger cubs at the Beijing Zoo
are the latest of a number of species
that have been cloned back into
existence in the past five years.
JAKE : I became a marine
for the hardship.
To be hammered
on the anvil of life.
I told myself I can pass
any test a man can pass.
(ROCK MUSIC BLARING)
ALL : (CHANTING) Jake! Jake! Jake!
Jake! Jake!
Oh!
JAKE : Let's get it
straight, upfront.
I don't want your pity.
You want a fair deal,
you're on the wrong planet.
(INDISTINCT)
The strong prey on the weak.
That's just the way
things are.
And nobody does
a damn thing.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(GRUNTING)
WOMAN : Get off!
Get off of him!
JAKE : All I ever wanted in my sorry-ass life
was a single thing worth fighting for.
(GRUNTS)
(GROANS)
(MAN LAUGHS)
I hope you realized you just
lost yourself a customer.
(DOOR SLAMS)
Candy-ass bitch.
(PANTING)
If it ain't raining,
we ain't training.
(CHUCKLES)
It doesn't look like him.
It's him.
You Jake Sully?
Step off.
You're ruining my good mood.
It's about
your brother.
We're looking
for Sully, T.
In there.
Jesus, Tommy.
JAKE : The strong prey
on the weak.
A guy with a knife took
all Tommy would ever be
for the paper in his wallet.
The concern of the suits
was touching.
Your brother represented
a significant investment.
We'd like to talk to you about
taking over his contract.
And since your genome
is identical to his,
you could step
into his shoes,
so to speak.
It'd be a fresh start
on a new world.
You could do something important.
You can make a difference.
And the pay is good.
Very good.
JAKE : Tommy was the scientist,
not me.
He was the one who wanted to get
shot light-years out in space
to find the answers.
Me, I was just another dumb grunt getting
sent someplace he was gonna regret.
(SIGHS)
(MONITOR BEEPING)
In cryo, you don't
dream at all.
It doesn't feel
like six years.
More like a fifth of tequila
and an ass-kicking.
Are we there yet?
Yeah, we're there,
sunshine.
We're there.
You've been in cryo for five
years, nine months and 22 days.
You will be hungry.
You will be weak.
If you feel nausea, please use the
sacks provided for your convenience.
The staff thanks you
in advance.
JAKE : Up ahead was Pandora.
You grew up hearing about it, but I
never figured I'd be going there.
MAN : Valkyrie 1-6, copy...
Valkyrie 1-6, you are clear for
de-orbit burn at 2-2-4-niner.
Copy, Venture Star.
Go for de-orbit burn at 2-2-4-niner.
Exo-packs on! Let's go!
Exo-packs on!
ASSISTANT : Exo-packs on!
Let's go!
Remember, people,
you lose that mask,
you're unconscious in 20 seconds,
you're dead in four minutes!
Let's nobody be dead today!
Looks very bad on my report.
Hell's Gate tower, this
is TAV 1-6 on approach.
Crossing outer marker.
Mine is in sight.
Harnesses off!
Get your packs!
Put it together, let's go! Let's go!
ASSISTANT : Harnesses off! One minute!
When that ramp comes down, go
directly into the base. Do not stop!
Go straight inside.
Wait for my mark!
Go, go, go, go! Get out of there!
Keep moving! Let's go, let's go!
JAKE : There's no such thing
as an ex-Marine.
You may be out, but you
never lose the attitude.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
Let's go, special case!
Do not make me wait for you!
Well, well,
ladies.
Look at all this
fresh meat! Whoo!
JAKE : Back on Earth, these
guys were Army dogs, Marines,
fighting for freedom.
AMPSUIT OPERATOR :
Look out, hot rod!
JAKE : But out here
they're just hired guns,
taking the money,
working for the company.
Check this out, man.
Meals on wheels.
Oh, man,
that is just wrong.
MAN #1 : I got two guys
free in about 20 minutes!
MAN #2 : Got it!
Need them!
QUARITCH : You're not
in Kansas any more.
You are on Pandora,
ladies and gentlemen.
Respect that fact
every second of every day.
If there is a hell,
you might want to go
there for some R&R
after a tour
on Pandora.
Out there,
beyond that fence,
every living thing that crawls,
flies or squats in the mud
wants to kill you and eat
your eyes for Jujubes.
We have an indigenous population
of humanoids called the Na'vi.
They're fond of arrows
dipped in a neurotoxin
that'll stop your heart
in one minute.
And they have bones reinforced with
naturally occurring carbon fiber.
They are very hard
to kill.
As head of security, it is
my job to keep you alive.
I will not succeed.
Not with all of you.
If you wish
to survive,
you need to cultivate
a strong mental attitude.
You've got to
obey the rules.
Pandora rules.
Rule number one...
JAKE : There's nothing like
an old-school safety brief
to put your mind at ease.
Excuse me. Excuse me. Jake!
You're Jake, right?
Tom's brother.
Wow! You look
just like him.
Sorry, I'm Norm.
Spellman.
I went through avatar
training with him.
(CHUCKLING)
...into the bio-lab.
We're gonna spend
a lot of time up here.
Hey! How you doing?
Norm, avatar driver.
FEMALE SCIENTIST : Hi.
MALE SCIENTIST : Hey.
Link...
Here's the link room right here.
This is where we're
connecting to the avatar.
JAKE : Me and Norm
are here to drive
these remotely controlled
bodies called avatars.
And they're grown from human DNA
mixed with the DNA of the natives.
Hey. Welcome.
Hey.
Welcome to Pandora.
Good to have you.
Thanks.
(LAUGHS) Damn!
They got big.
Yeah, they fully mature
on the flight out.
So the proprioceptive sims
seem to work really well.
Yeah, they've got
great muscle tone.
It'll take us a few hours
to get them decanted,
but you guys can take
them out tomorrow.
There's yours.
Hey.
Dr. Norm Spellman.
Dr. Max Patel. Great to meet you.
NORM : Good to meet you, yeah.
(HEARTBEAT THUMPING)
Looks like him.
No, it looks like you.
NORM : This is
your avatar now, Jake.
JAKE : And the concept is that every
driver is matched to his own avatar,
so that their nervous
systems are in tune,
or something.
Which is why they
offered me the gig,
because I can link
with Tommy's avatar,
which is
insanely expensive.
Is this right?
I just say whatever to the video log?
Yeah, we gotta get in the habit
of documenting everything.
You know, what we
see, what we feel.
It's all part
of the science.
And good science
is good observation.
Plus it'll help to keep you
sane for the next six years.
All right.
Whatever.
So, uh...
Well, here I am,
doing science.
MALE TECHNICIAN :
They're coming out!
WOMAN ON PA : Attention.
Drivers coming out of link.
(SIGHING)
Oh, God.
(GROANS)
FEMALE TECH : Where's the lab coat?
Where's the lab coat?
Who's got my goddamn
cigarette?
Guys! What's wrong
with this picture?
Thank you!
NORM : Grace Augustine
is a legend.
She's the head of the Avatar Program.
She wrote the book,
I mean, literally wrote the
book on Pandoran botany.
Well, that's 'cause she likes
plants better than people.
Here she is, Cinderella
back from the ball.
Grace, I'd like you to meet
Norm Spellman and Jake Sully.
Norm. I hear good things about you.
How's your Na'vi?
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
...but there is much to learn.
(CHUCKLES)
Grace?
This is Jake Sully.
Ma'am.
Yeah, yeah.
I know who you are,
and I don't need you.
I need your brother.
You know, the PhD who trained for
three years for this mission?
He's dead.
I know it's a big
inconvenience for everyone.
How much lab training
have you had?
I dissected
a frog once.
You see? You see?
I mean, they're just pissing on us
without even the courtesy
of calling it rain.
I'm going to Self ridge.
No, Grace,
I don't think that's a good idea.
No, man, this is such bullshit!
I'm gonna kick
his corporate butt.
He has no business sticking
his nose in my department.
Here tomorrow, 0800.
Try and use big words.
(PEOPLE CHATTERING ON RADIO)
Scorpion Two-Hotel,
Hell's Gate tower.
You are cleared
for south departure.
Hover taxi, Delta runway.
Squawk ident.
Mmm! You see that? Yes, sir.
No, you didn't.
You were looking at the monitor.
I love this putter, Ronnie!
I love this putter.
Parker, you know, I used to
think it was benign neglect,
but now I see that you're
intentionally screwing me.
Grace, you know, I enjoy
our little talks.
Oops.
I need a researcher.
Not some jarhead dropout.
Well, actually, I thought
we got lucky with him.
Lucky?
Yeah.
How is this
in any way lucky?
Lucky your guy
had a twin brother,
and lucky that brother wasn't
some oral hygienist or something.
A Marine
we can use.
I'm assigning him to your
team as security escort.
The last thing I need is another
trigger-happy moron out there!
Look, look, you're supposed
to be winning the hearts
and the minds
of the natives.
Isn't that the whole point
of your little puppet show?
If you look like them
and you talk like them,
then they'll start
trusting us.
We build them a school,
we teach them English,
but after, what,
how many years?
Relations with the indigenous
are only getting worse.
Yeah, that tends
to happen
when you use
machine guns on them.
Right. Come here.
I can't...
This is why we're here.
Unobtanium.
Because this little gray rock
sells for 20 million a kilo.
That's the only reason.
It's what pays for the whole party.
It's what pays
for your science.
Comprendo?
Now, those savages are
threatening our whole operation,
we're on the brink of war,
and you're supposed to be
finding a diplomatic solution.
So use what you've got,
and get me some results.
(PEOPLE CHATTERING)
So, how much link time
have you logged?
About 520 hours.
That's good.
You're in there.
You're here.
How much
have you logged?
Zip. But I read
a manual.
Tell me
you're joking.
This is cool.
Let's go.
Don't. I got this.
(SIGHING) So you just figured
you'd come out here,
to the most hostile
environment known to man,
with no training of any
kind, and see how it went?
What was going
through your head?
Maybe I was sick of doctors
telling me what I couldn't do.
Biometrics are good.
Link three is ready.
Keep your arms in,
handsin,
head down.
Down. Just relax and let
your mind go blank.
That shouldn't be
hard for you.
(CHUCKLING) Kiss the darkest
part of my lily white...
Initiate link.
Run sequence
unit three. Go.
LINK TECH :
Launching.
I have the first
congruency.
That's a gorgeous brain.
Nice activity.
Hmm. Go figure.
Phase-lock 40%.
All right.
Going in.
I'm going in
in four.
Phase-lock 99%.
Link is stable.
(RESPIRATOR HISSING)
(DISTANTLY) He's in.
Jake, can you hear me?
Can you hear me, Jake?
Pupillary reflex
is good.
Pinna response normal.
How you feeling, Jake?
Hey, guys.
(CHUCKLES) Welcome to
your new body, Jake.
FEMALE TECH : G0od!
Yeah, we're gonna take
this nice and easy, Jake.
And touch your thumb
to your fingers. Yeah.
Thumb to your fingers.
No problem.
That's good.
I can see you can remember that one.
Got it.
Well, if you want
to sit up,
that's fine. Okay, good.
Just take it
nice and slow,
Jake. Good.
Okay, well, no truncal
ataxia, that's good.
Are you feeling lightheaded
or dizzy at all?
You're wiggling
your toes!
MALE TECH : Good. Good, Jake.
That's great.
(JAKE GASPING IN AMAZEMENT)
Distal motor control is good.
Good, Jake.
Are you feeling
any numbness or pain?
That's great, Jake. Hold on, now.
FEMALE TECH : Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Take it easy.
Don't get ahead of yourself, okay?
There's a few more sensory motor
reflex tests we need to run,
so take it easy.
Ooh! Wait.
Jake.
Sit down, Jake.
Jake! Listen to me. Jake! Whoa.
I need you to sit down.
Jake! It's okay.
Buddy, listen to me.
It's all good. I got this.
Jake, you need to
sit down right now.
Guys, get him back
on the gurney now.
Listen to me. For your own
safety, you need to sit down.
You need time to adjust to the avatar...
Whoa! Jake!
God, Jake,
watch your tail.
(LAUGHING) Yeah!
Sedate! Sedate him!
A thousand milligrams of Supitocam! Stat!
MAX : Guys! Guys!
Whoa! Whoa!
NORM ON INTERCOM :
By the numbers.
Jake. Come on.
Jake! Listen to me.
You're not used
to your avatar body.
This is dangerous.
This is great.
MAX : Jake? Jake, listen to me.
Come on. They're gonna put you out.
(JAKE LAUGHING)
MALE TECH :
Norm, sit down.
No, no. I gotta get
out of these leads.
God damn it!
Bring them home!
Norm! Do not
leave control!
FEMALE TECH :
You're not ready for it!
Oh, come on, you
ain't got no skills.
Ooh! Ooh! So close!
I don't even have
to play defense on it.
Hey, guys. Hey.
MALE AVATAR : Whoa.
NORM : It's okay,
I'll get him.
Jake, you have
to come back!
Jake!Jake!
Excuse me.
Watch it!
Sorry!
Come on!
Jake! We're not
supposed to be running!
(LAUGHING)
(PANTING)
(GRUNTING)
Jeez! Sorry.
Watch it!
GRACE : Hey, Marine!
Damn.
Grace?
Well, who'd you
expect, numbnuts?
Think fast.
Motor control's
looking good.
(CHUCKLING APPRECIATIVELY)
(CHUCKLES)
GRACE : Come on, everybody,
quiet down!
All right, gang,
lights out.
Come on, Louise,
chop-chop.
Hey, hey, hey!
GRACE : Don't play with that,
you'll go blind.
That's kind of freaky.
Come on. Scat.
Good night.
Lights out!
See you at dinner, kiddies.
(CREATURES SCREECHING)
(SIGHS)
(GASPS)
MAX : Welcome back.
You okay?
You all right?
Yeah, I'm okay.
I'm Trudy. I fly all the science sorties.
And this here is my baby.
Hold on a second.
Hey, Wainﬂeet!
Get it done!
We bounce
at zero-nine.
Yeah, I'm on it,
capitaine!
Vine strike's
still loose.
You guys are packing
some heavy gear.
Watch it!
Yeah, that's 'cause we're not the
only thing flying around out there.
Or the biggest.
I'm gonna need you on a door gun.
I'm a man short.
I thought
you'd never ask.
There's your man.
See you on the flight line.
You wanted to
see me, Colonel?
This low gravity'll
make you soft.
You get soft,
Pandora will shit you out
dead with zero warning.
I pulled your record,
Corporal.
Venezuela, that was
some mean bush.
Nothing like this
here, though.
You got some
heart, kid,
showing up in
this neighborhood.
I figured it's just
another hellhole.
I was First Recon myself.
A few years ahead of you.
Well, maybe more than a few.
Three tours Nigeria,
not a scratch.
I come out here?
Day one. Think I felt
like a shavetail louie?
Yeah. Oh, they could fix
me up, if I rotated back.
Yeah, and make me
pretty again.
But you know what?
I kind of like it.
It reminds me every day
what's waiting out there.
Hup! The Avatar Program
is a bad joke.
Bunch of limp-dick
science majors.
However, it does present an
opportunity both timely and unique.
Clear!
MAN : Clear!
(POWERING UP)
A recon gyrene in an avatar body.
That's a potent mix.
Give me the goose bumps.
Such a Marine could
provide the intel I need,
right on the ground.
Right in
the hostiles' camp.
Look, Sully. I want you to learn
these savages from the inside.
I want you
to gain their trust.
I need to know how to
force their cooperation
or hammer them hard
if they won't.
Am I still
with Augustine?
On paper.
Yeah, you walk like one of her
science pukes, you quack like one,
but you report to me.
Can you do that
for me, son?
Hell, yeah, sir.
Well, all right, then.
Son, I take care
of my own.
You get me
what I need,
I'll see to it you get your
legs back when you rotate home.
Your real legs.
That sounds
real good, sir.
Link's ready!
LINK TECH :
Phase-lock 40%.
Just keep your mouth shut
and let Norm do the talking.
LINK TECH : I have five congruencies.
Phase-lock 90%.
MAX : Link three ready.
GRACE : All right,
I'm going in.
(SQUAWKING)
Sturmbeest herd
coming up on your right.
Got it! Thanks.
Looks like a bull, a dozen
cows and some juveniles.
(GROWLING)
(ROARING)
(WHOOPING)
(CHUCKUNG)
Shut it down.
We're gonna stay a while.
Norm! Your pack.
Pack.
Stay with the ship.
One idiot with a gun is enough.
You the man, Doc.
(DISTANT YOWLING)
(CREATURE COOING)
(SQUEAKING)
Prolemuris.
They're not aggressive.
Relax, Marine.
You're making me nervous.
NORM : So, how will
they know we're here?
GRACE : I'm sure they're
watching us right now.
This was our school.
Now it's just...storage.
The kids were so bright.
Eager to learn.
They picked up English faster
than I could teach it.
So, we'll take a couple
of these Ph monitors...
...and a soil probe.
That little yellow case back there.
The old microscope.
Here.
Oh, yeah.
I love this one.
The stingbats
knocked them down.
(SCREECHING)
GRACE : I keep hoping someone
will come back in and read them.
NORM : Why don't
they come back?
The Omaticaya...learned as much
about us as they needed to.
What happened here?
Are you going to help us with this gear?
We've got a lot to do.
JAKE : Keep moving, Norm.
GRACE : Keep up, guys!
GRACE : And here I go.
NORM : Scanning.
Oh, wow!
It's that fast?
(LAUGHING)
Amazing, isn't it?
Yeah.
So, that is signal
transduction from this root
to the root of the tree next to it.
So, we should take a sample.
NORM : Okay. Sample.
NORM : You know,
it's probably electrical,
based on the speed
of the reaction.
GRACE : Norm, you've contaminated
the sample with your saliva.
NORM : Right.
(GASPS)
GRACE : So, here I go.
(GRACE CONTINUES CHATTERING)
(LAUGHING)
(TRUMPETING)
Don't shoot. Don't shoot,
you'll piss him off.
(TRUMPETING)
It's already pissed off.
Jake, that
armor's too thick.
Trust me.
It's a territorial
threat display.
Do not run,
or he'll charge.
So, what do I do,
dance with it?
Just hold your ground.
(GROWLING)
(TRUMPETING)
(SCREAMING)
(SCREECHING)
(LAUGHING NERVOUSLY)
Yeah? Come on!
What you got?
Oh, yeah. Who's bad?
That's right.
Yeah, that's what
I'm talking about, bitch.
That's right, get your
punk ass back to mommy.
Yeah? Yeah, you got nothing.
You keep running.
Yeah, and why don't you bring
back some of your friends, huh?
(SNARLING SOFTLY)
(ROARING)
Oh, shit.
(CREATURES ROARING)
So what about this one?
Run? Don't run? What?
Run! Definitely run!
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMING)
(ROARING)
(GRUNTS)
I'm gonna have
to call it, guys.
We're not allowed to run night ops.
Colonel's orders.
I'm sorry, Doc, he's just gonna
have to hang on till morning.
He won't make it
till morning.
(CREATURES CHITTERING)
(PANTING)
(GROWLING)
(CREATURES GROWLING)
(CREATURES HISSING)
(GROWLING)
(GRUNTING)
(CHITTERING)
(SNARLING)
(SNARLS)
(HISSING)
I don't have
all goddamn night.
Come on!
(YELP5)
(YELPING)
(GRUNTING)
(SNARLING)
(YELP5)
(YELLING)
(YELPING)
(GRUNTING)
(HISSING)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
JAKE : Hey, wait.
Don't!
(SCOFFS)
Great.
(WHIMPERING)
(GRUNTS)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
(WHIMPERING STOPS)
Look, I know you probably
don't understand this,
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
but thank you.
Thank you.
That was
pretty impressive.
I would have been screwed if you
hadn't come along. It was...
Hey, wait a second.
Hey, where you going?
Wait up!
Just... Hey, slow down.
Look, wait up, I just wanted to say
thanks for killing those things.
(EXCLAIMS IN PAIN)
Damn!
Don't thank.
You don't thank
for this.
This is sad.
Very sad only.
Okay. Okay.
I'm sorry.
Whatever I did,
I am sorry.
NEYTIRI : All this is your fault.
They did not need to die.
JAKE : My fault? They attacked me.
How am I the bad guy?
Whoa!
Your fault!
(GENTLY) Shh.
Easy. Easy.
NEYTIRI : You're like a baby.
Making noise, don't know what to do.
Easy. Shh.
Fine. Fine.
JAKE : If you love your little
forest friends,
why not let them
just kill my ass?
What's the thinking?
WW save you?
Yeah. Yeah,
why save me?
NEYTIRI : You have
a strong heart.
No fear.
But stupid!
Ignorant like a child.
(SCOFFS)
JAKE : Well, if I'm like
a child, then...
Look, maybe you should teach me.
Sky People cannot learn.
You do not See.
Well, then teach me
how to See.
No one can
teach you to See.
Whoa.
Look, come on,
can't we talk?
Say, where'd you learn
to speak English?
Dr. Augustine's school?
(GRUNTING)
You're like
a baby.
(SIGHS)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
I need your help.
You should not
be here.
Okay, take me
with you.
No! Go back.
No.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Go back.
(EXCLAIMING IN NA'VI)
No!
(SPEAKING SHARPLY IN NA'VI)
(REPEATS SOFTLY)
What...
What are they?
Seeds of
the Sacred Tree.
Very pure spirits.
Uh-huh.
(CHUCKLES)
What was that
all about?
(WHISPERING IN NA'VI)
Come.
Come!
Where are we going?
Come.
What's your name?
Shit!
(GROANING)
(GASPS)
(ALL ULULATING)
(CHUCKLES NERVOUSLY)
Okay.
(YELLS)
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
Calm People, calm.
What are you doing, Tsu'tsy?
(SPEAKING IN NA'VI)
These demons are Forbidden here
This is a matter For the Tsahik.
Bring him.
What's going on?
(GROANING) Wait.
(ORDERING IN NA'VI)
What's happening?
Hey!
(VILLAGERS CHATTERING)
(HUNTERS WHOOPING)
(NEYTIRI SPEAKING NA'VI)
Father...
...I see you.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
This creature...
...why do gou bring him here?
I was going to kill him...
His alien smell fills my nose.
What's he saying?
His alien smell xcills mg nose.
Hey, what's he saying?
My father is deciding
whether to kill you.
Your father.
It's nice to meet you, sir.
(ALL EXCLAIMING IN NA'VI)
(MO'AT SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
Step back!
I will look at this alien.
That is Mother.
She is Tsahik. The one who
interprets the will of Eyvva.
Who's Eywa?
(IN ENGLISH)
What are you called?
Jake Sully.
(GRUNTS)
Why did you
come to us?
I came to learn.
We have tried to teach
other Sky People.
It is hard to fill a cup
which is already full.
Well, my cup is empty,
trust me.
Just ask Dr. Augustine.
I'm no scientist.
What are you?
I was a Marine. A...
A warrior of
the Jarhead clan.
I could him easily!
No!
We need to learn more about him
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Why me? That's not fair...
(EXCLAIMS IN ANNOYANCE)
It is decided.
My daughter will teach you our ways.
Learn well,
Jakesully.
Then we will see if your
insanity can be cured.
(VILLAGERS CHATTERING)
(DRUMS BEATING)
(SINGING IN NA'VI)
(CHATTERING AND SINGING STOP)
(STAMMERING)
Good evening.
Please don't get up.
Excuse me.
(EXCLAIMS)
Sorry.
(CHATTERING
AND SINGING RESUME)
Hey, how you doing?
Thank you.
You know, I don't
even know your name.
Neytiri te
Ckaha Mo'at'ite.
Again, a whole
lot slower?
Neytiri.
Neytili.
(ENUNCIATING) Neytiri.
Neytiri.
It's nice to
meet you, Neytiri.
It's nice.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(GRUNTING)
GRACE : (ECHOING) Jake.Jake!
MAX : He's in alpha.
He's coming out
right now.
Jake.Jake!
GRACE : Come on back, kid.
Come on. That's it.
(GASPING IN CONFUSION)
There you go.
There you go, there you go.
You're okay.
Damn! You were
dug in like a tick.
(GROANING)
(SIGHS)
ls the avatar safe?
Yeah, Doc.
And you are not gonna
believe where I am.
(LAUGHS)
The last thing we see
is this Marine's ass
disappearing into the brush with this
angry thanator coming after him.
Hey, it's not something
you can teach.
MAX : That is awesome.
You know, for reasons
I cannot fathom,
the Omaticaya have chosen you.
God help us all.
(MEN LAUGHING)
"Jarhead clan"?
Mmm-hmm.
(LAUGHING)
And it worked?
Hey,
I'm practically family.
They're gonna study me.
I have to learn to be one of them.
That's called taking
the initiative, son.
I wish I had
10 more like you.
Look, Sully. Sully.
Just find out what
the blue monkeys want.
You know, I mean, we try to give
them medicine, education, roads.
But no ,no, no,
they like mud.
And that wouldn't bother me,
it's just that they're...
Hey, can you...
Can somebody just... Sector 12.
Go: go! go'
stop. Stop...
Rich, stop!
That's... Jesus!
Their damn village happens to be resting
on the richest unobtanium deposit
within 200 klicks
in any direction.
I mean, look at
all that cheddar!
(LAUGHS)
Well, who gets
them to move?
Guess.
(SCOFFS)
What if
they won't go?
Oh, I'm betting
that they will.
Okay, okay, okay, okay, hey.
Look. Look.
Killing the indigenous
looks bad,
but there's one thing that
shareholders hate more than bad press,
and that's a bad
quarterly statement.
I didn't make
up the rules.
So just find me a carrot
that'll get them to move,
otherwise it's gonna have
to be all stick. Okay?
You got three months.
That's when the 'dozers get there.
Well,
we're wasting time.
I like this guy.
MAX : Guys, right now...
GRACE : Okay, let's run
through them again.
M0'at. Dragon lady.
Eytucan. Eytukan.
He's the clan leader.
But she's the
spiritual leader.
Like a shaman.
Got it.
T'su'tey.
Tsu'tey.
He'll be the next
clan leader.
Neytiri.
She'll be
the next Tsahik.
They become
a mated pair.
So who's this Eyvva?
(SHOCKED) Who's Eyvva?
Only their deity.
Their goddess, made up of all living things.
Everything they know!
You'd know this if you had
any training whatsoever.
Who's got a date with
the chief's daughter?
Come on. That's not a...
Knock it off.
It's like kindergarten around here.
Neytiri was
my best student.
She and her sister,
Sylwanin.
Just amazing girls.
I got a date
with Sylwanin too.
She's dead.
Let's go.
Village life starts early.
Don't do anything
unusually stupid.
JAKE : Easy, boy.
Pale is female.
(NEYTIRI SPEAKING
SOOTHINGLY IN NA'VI)
JAKE : Okay.
Easy, girl.
(GRUNTING)
(SPEAKING SOOTHINGLY IN NA'VI)
(WHINNYING)
(EXHALING)
That is shahaylu.
The bond.
Feel her.
Feel her heartbeat.
Her breath.
Feel her strong legs.
You may tell her
what to do.
Inside.
For now,
say where to go.
Forward!
(GRUNTING)
(LAUGHING)
You should go away.
No, you'd miss me.
I knew you could
speak English.
(SCOFFING)
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
This alien will learn nothing...
...a rock sess mors...
...look at him.
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
Again.
JAKE : If you want
to hit this thing,
it's gonna be
complicated.
Your scan doesn't show
the internal structure.
There's an outer row of columns.
QUARITCH : Uh-huh.
Real heavy duty.
There's a secondary ring here,
and an inner ring.
There's a core structure
like a spiral.
That's how they
move up and down.
We're gonna need accurate
scans on every column.
Roger that.
What else can you tell
us about the structure?
JAKE : I'm guessing this secondary
ring, that's also load-bearing.
So where are
we going?
Getting out of Dodge.
I'm not about to let Self ridge and
Quaritch micro-manage this thing.
There's a mobile link up at
Site 26 we can work out of,
way up
in the mountains.
The Hallelujah Mountains?
That's right.
Are you serious?
Yeah.
Yes!
(NORM LAUGHING)
The legendary floating
mountains of Pandora.
Heard of them?
We're getting close.
Yeah, look at
my instruments.
Yep. We're in
the Flux Vortex.
We're VFR
from here on.
What's VFR?
Means you gotta see
where you're going.
You can't see anything.
(LAUGHING) Exactly.
Ain't that a bitch?
Oh, my God.
(LAUGHING) You should
see your faces.
Thank you for
flying Air Pandora.
JAKE : So what does
hold them up?
Grace explained it to me.
Some kind of maglev effect.
Because unobtanium is a superconductor...
or something.
(AIRLOCK HISSING)
Welcome to camp.
GRACE : So, this is my bunk.
This stuff is nasty.
GRACE : Norm, go under.
NORM : All right.
JAKE : Grace didn't
miss a thing.
GRACE : Trudy,
you'll take the top one.
She knew I was talking
to the Colonel.
But I had what she needed,
a way back in with the clan,
so she's playing nice.
All right. Jake,
hang a left.
You'll be in the
link at the end.
Unit one. Beulah.
She's the least glitchy.
(IMITATING BIRD CALL)
(BIRDS CAWING)
(SQUAWKING)
(LAUGHING NERVOUSLY)
Holy shit!
Do not look
in her eye.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
lkran is not horse.
Once shahaylu is made,
ikran will fly with only one
hunter in the whole life.
To become taronyu,
hunter,
you must choose your own ikran
and he must choose you.
When?
When you are ready.
(EXCLAIMS)
(NEYTIRI WHOOPING)
Okay. This is
video log 12.
Time's 2132.
(SIGHING) Do I have
to do this now?
I really need to
get some rack.
No, now.
When it's fresh.
Okay, location,
shack,
and the days are starting
to blur together.
(SPEAKING NA'VI SLOWLY)
(REPEATING TENTATIVELY)
JAKE : The language
is a pain, but, you know,
I figure it's like
field-stripping a weapon.
Just repetition, repetition.
Na'vi.
"Nari."
Nari.
(IMPATIENTLY) "Narrri"!
Narrri!
Txur ni'ul.
Stronger.
(INHALES)
JAKE : Neytiri calls me skxawng.
It means moron.
This is a very important
part of it.
Norm 's attitude
has improved lately.
I see you. I see you.
But it's not just, "I'm
seeing you in front of me,"
it's "I see into you.
I See you."
It's good
he's back on board,
but he thinks
I'm a skxawng, too.
"I'm accepting you.
I understand you."
So you gotta
get this, okay?
I gotta run! Okay?
Let's go.
My feet are getting tougher.
I can run farther every day.
I have to trust my body
to know what to do.
Yeah! Check it out!
Oh, crap!
Every day
it's reading the trails,
the tracks at the waterhole,
the tiniest scents and sounds.
(CUSS SQUEAKING)
She's always going on about the flow
of energy, the spirits of animals.
I really hope this tree-hugger
crap isn't on the final.
This isn't just about eye-hand
coordination out there, you know.
You need to listen
to what she says.
Try to see the forest
through her eyes.
Excuse me.
This is my video log here.
With Neytiri,
it's learn fast or die.
You gotta be kidding me.
(SCREAMING)
(BRANCHES CRACKING)
(GRUNTING)
(EXCLAIMS)
(PANTING)
(GROANING)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
I talked Mo'at into letting
Grace into the village.
You are so pretty.
It's the first time since her
school was closed down.
You are so Pretty.
(CHILDREN LAUGHING)
(POWERING OFF)
(GENTLY)
Come on, Marine.
JAKE : I'm trying to understand this deep
connection the people have to the forest.
She talks about
a network of energy
that flows through
all living things.
She says all energy
is only borrowed,
and one day you have
to give it back.
(CHIRPING)
(EXCLAIMS)
(CHUCKUNG)
(LAUGHING)
You were in
16 hours today.
You're still
losing weight.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
No, you don't.
I gotta get some sleep.
Come back here.
Bon appétit.
Today I made a kill.
And we ate it. At least, I know
where that meal came from.
Other body. You need to take
care of this body. Okay?
Get it? Let's eat it.
Yeah, yeah.
Here. I'll make it
easy for you.
(CHUCKLING)
Give it to me.
You look like crap.
Thank you.
You're burning
way too hard.
Get rid of this shit.
And then you
can lecture me.
Now, I'm telling you,
as your boss,
and as someone who might even
consider being a friend someday
(CHUCKLES)
to take some
down time.
Eat this, please.
Trust me, I...
learned the hard way.
(BEEPS)
What did happen
at the school, Grace?
(SIGHS)
Neytiri's sister, Sylwanin,
stopped coming to school.
She was angry about
the clear-cutting.
And one day, she and a couple of
other young hunters came running in
all painted up.
They had set
a bulldozer on fire.
I guess they thought
I could protect them.
The troopers pursued
them to the school.
They killed Sylwanin
in the doorway.
Right in front
of Neytiri.
And then shot
the others.
I got most of
the kids out.
But they never
came back.
I'm sorry.
A scientist
stays objective.
We can't be
ruled by emotion.
But I put 10 years of my
life into that school.
They called me sa'nok.
Mother.
That kind of pain reaches
back through the link.
(GROWLS)
(MOANING)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
...l5rotl1cr
and thank 5011
(STABS)
Your spirit goes with Egwa.
Your 130015 stays behind
---to become Part 0? The Peep
A clean kill.
You are ready.
JAKE : Learning to ride an ikran,
we call them banshees,
is the test every
young hunter has to pass.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
But to do that, you gotta
go where the banshees are.
O0-rah.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Now what?
(COMMANDS IN NA'VI)
(GRUNTING)
(GRUNTS)
(NEYTIRI WHOOPING)
(SCREECHING)
(EXCLAIMING)
(NEYTIRI SPEAKING NA'VI)
(SPEAKING SOFTLY IN NA'VI)
(PANTING)
Jakesully will go first.
(EXHALES SHARPLY)
(SCREECHING)
Now you choose your ikran.
This you must feel inside.
If he also chooses you,
move quick like I showed.
You will have
one chance, Jake.
How will I know
if he chooses me?
He will try
to kill you.
Outstanding.
(EXCLAIMS)
(HISSING)
(GRUNTS)
(EXCLAIMING)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
(ROARING)
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
(HISSING)
Let's dance.
(LAUGHING)
That moron's going to die.
(SCREECHING)
(WHOOPING)
(GRUNTING)
Don't be afraid, warrior.
Make the bond!
(GRUNTING) No!
(EXCLAIMS)
Jake!
(LAUGHING)
(GRUNTING)
(IKRAN SCREECHING)
(SHOUTING)
Shahaylu, Jake.
NEYTIRI : Shahaylu!
(YELLING)
Stop!
(SPEAKING SOFTLY IN NA'VI)
(CHUCKLES) Yeah, that's right.
You're mine. Huh?
First flight seals the bond.
You cannot wait.
Think, "Fly!"
Fly?
(EXCLAIMING)
(SCREAMING)
God damn!
Oh, shit!
(YELLING)
(SCREECHING)
Shut up and
fly straight!
(JAKE PANTING)
That's it.
Bank left!
Level out!
That's it.
(HUNTERS WHOOPING)
WARRIOR: Whoo!
Jakesullyl
(WHOOPING)
(SPEAKS SHARPLY
IN NA'VI)
(CHUCKUNG)
(NEYTIRI HOOTING)
Hey!
Let's go!
Yeah, baby,
I got this!
Oh, shit!
(WHOOPING)
JAKE : I may not be
much of a horse guy,
but I was born to do this.
(CHUCKLES) Yeah!
I came like this.
This you. Yeah, yeah.
I turn. I feel the wind.
I turn very strong.
Look,yeah,see,
I banked so hard...
(GASPS)
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
(LAUGHING)
(JAKE WHOOPING)
GRACE : The Tree of Souls.
(TRANSLATING INTO NA'VI)
It's their most
sacred place.
See the Flux Vortex in
these false color images?
Yeah, that's what messes
up my instruments.
There is something really interesting
going on in there biologically.
I would die
to get samples.
Outsiders are
strictly forbidden.
GRACE : You lucky swine.
(WHOOPING)
(ROARING)
(EXCLAIMING)
(GRUNTS)
(YELLS)
(ROARING)
Hell, yeah!
(WHOOPING)
(NEYTIRI ULULATING)
JAKE : I was
a stone-cold aerial hunter.
Death from above.
Only problem is,
you're not the only one.
(JAKE AND NEYTIRI
EXCHANGING YELPS)
Dive!
(ROARING)
(SCREECHING)
Go, go!
(NEYTIRI IMITATING BIRD CRIES)
Follow me!
(ROARING)
(SOFTLY) Whew.
(BOTH HOOTING)
(SPEAKING SOOTHINGLY IN NA'VI)
(SHUSHING)
(BOTH LAUGHING)
Our guys call it
a Great Leonopteryx.
It is Toruk.
Last Shadow.
Yeah, right.
It's the last one you ever see.
My grandfather's grandfather
was Toruk Macto.
Rider of Last Shadow.
He rode this?
Toruk chose him.
It has only happened five times
since the time of the First Songs.
That's a long time.
Yes.
Toruk Macto was mighty.
He brought the clans together
in a time of great sorrow.
All Na'vi people
know the story.
(INHALING DEEPLY)
JAKE : Everything is
backwards now.
Like out there
is the true world
and in here
is the dream.
(SIGHS)
It's hard to believe it's
only been three months.
I can barely remember
my old life.
I don't know
who I am any more.
(SNIFFLES)
Haven't gotten lost in
the woods, have you?
Your last report was
more than two weeks ago.
I'm starting to
doubt your resolve!
The way I see it, it's time
to terminate the mission.
No, I can do this.
You already have.
You give me good,
usable intel.
This Tree of Souls place.
Yeah, I got them
by the balls with that
when this turns
into a shit fight,
which it Will. Yeah.
Now it's time
to come in.
By the way,
you gonna get
your legs back.
Yeah. I got your corporate approval.
It's a done deal.
Gonna have you
on a shuttle tonight.
I'm a man of my word.
I gotta finish this.
There's one more thing.
Ceremony. It's the final
stage of becoming a man.
If I do it,
I'm one of them.
And they'll trust me.
And I can negotiate the
terms of their relocation.
Well, then, you'd better
get it done, Corporal.
JAKE : The Na 'vi say that
every person is born twice.
The second time is when you earn your
place among The People forever.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
You are now a son of the Omaticaga.
You are part of The People.
(SNIFFLING SOFTLY)
(LAUGHING)
Come. Come.
(LAUGHS)
This is a place for
prayers to be heard.
And sometimes answered.
(SIGHS)
We call these trees
Utraya Mokri.
The Tree of Voices.
The voices of
our ancestors.
(VOICES WHISPERING)
(VOICES CHATTERING DISTANTLY)
I can hear them.
They live, Jake,
within Eyvva.
(CHILDREN LAUGHING)
NEYTIRI : You are Omaticaya now.
You may make your bow
from the wood of Hometree.
And you may
choose a woman.
We have many
fine women.
Ninat is the best singer.
JAKE : But I don't want Ninat.
(BLOWING)
NEYTIRI : Beyral is a good hunter.
JACK: Yeah, she is
a good hunter.
(EXHALES)
(SOFTLY)
I've already chosen.
But this woman must
also choose me.
She already has.
(GASPS)
I am with you now, Jake.
We are mated for life.
JAKE : What the hell
are you doing, Jake?
(MACHINERY RUMBLING)
(BRANCH CRACKING)
(MACHINERY APPROACHING)
(GASPING)
(ENGINES RUMBLING)
Ma Jake!
NORM : Don't forget
your phase integration.
GRACE : Jake!
No, no, the middle button.
You gotta eat something.
Yeah, there you go.
Jake!Jake. Wake up!
Jake, please!
Don't make me
force-feed a cripple.
(CHUCKLES) Grace,
I don't want... Hey!
(POWERING DOWN)
(GRUNTS IN ALARM)
Jake!
(CHUCKLING) Okay.
(GRUNTING)
Here. I'm done.
Let's go.
And when was the last
time you took a shower?
I don't need a shower.
Jesus, Marine.
(GRUNTING)
Jake!
Jake! Wake up!
Hey!
Stop! Stop!
NEYTIRI : Jake!
Go back, stop!
Hey, boss.
Hey!
(BULLDOZER POWERING DOWN)
What?
I got a native
doing the funky chicken here.
He's blocking my blade.
Well, keep going.
He'll move.
SELFRIDGE : These people have to learn
that we don't stop. Come on, go, go, go.
Stop! Hey!
GO! Go!
There, see?
He moved.
(GRUNTING)
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa,
whoa, whoa, whoa.
Dude,dude. VVhoa,dude! Dude,no!
Oh! I'm blind.
(GUNFIRE CONTINUES)
Jake!
Neytiri!
Here, come on!
(NEYTIRI SOBBING)
(INHALING)
QUARITCH :
Freeze it right there.
Scale up.
Enhance.
SELFRIDGE :
Son of a bitch.
Unbelievable.
Get me a pilot.
Yes, sir.
(HUNTERS HOOTING WAR CRIES)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Tsu'tey lead the war Party
(ALL SHOUTING WAR CRIES)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Stop Please. I
This will only make it worse.
You do not speak here!
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
We will strike them in the heart.
(ALL SHOUTING WAR CRIES)
JAKE : Tsu'tey!
Don't do this.
You!
Listen. Brother...
(SHOUTS IN NA'VI)
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
You mated with
this woman?
Oh, shit.
(STERNLY) Is this true?
We are mated before Eyvva.
It is done.
(BREATHING TREMULOUSLY)
JAKE : Brother, please.
Do not attack
the Sky People.
Many Omaticaya
will die if you do.
You are not my brother!
(YELLING)
And I am not
your enemy!
The enemy is out there,
and they are very powerful!
Go! Go! Go!
I can talk to them.
No more talk.
NEYTIRI :
Tsu'tey!
I am Omaticaya.
I am one of you.
And I have
the right to speak.
(SIGHS)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
I have something to sag...
...to all of you.
(IN ENGLISH) The words are
like stones in my heart.
NORM : Sir, I'm sorry.
No, no, no! Hold on!
You can't interrupt
a link in progress!
It's very dangerous!
NEYTIRI : Grace!
Oh, no.
Wait!
Stay down, sir.
(BEEPING)
Okay. Look...
I was sent here to...
(CROWD MURMURING)
(GRUNTS)
It is a demon in a false body.
(NEYTIRI YELLING)
(GROWLING)
(EXCLAIMS)
(GASPS)
Are you out of
your goddamn mind?
You crossed the line.
Wheel this meat
out of here.
GRACE : Jake!
What the hell is going on here?
QUARITCH :
You let me down, son.
So, what,
you find yourself
some local tail
and you just completely forget
what team you're playing for?
Parker, there is time
to salvage the situation.
Parker...
Shut your pie hole!
Or what, Ranger Rick?
You gonna shoot me?
I could do that.
You need to
muzzle your dog.
Yeah, can we just
take this down
a couple of notches,
please?
You say you want to
keep your people alive?
You start by
listening to her.
Those trees were sacred
to the Omaticaya
in a way you can't imagine.
You know what?
You throw a stick in
the air around here,
it's gonna land on
some sacred fern,
(MOCKINGLY) for Christ's sake!
I'm not talking
about some kind of
pagan voodoo here.
I'm talking about
something real,
something measurable
in the biology of the forest.
Which is what, exactly?
What we think we know
is that there is some kind of
electrochemical communication
between the roots
of the trees,
like the synapses
between neurons.
And each tree has ten-to-the-fourth
connections to the trees around it.
And there are ten-to-the-twelfth
trees on Pandora.
Which is a lot,
I'm guessing.
It's more connections
than the human brain.
Get it?
It's a network.
It's a global network, and
the Na'vi can access it.
They can upload and download data.
Memories.
At sites like the one
you just destroyed.
(IN AWE) Yes!
(LAUGHING) What the hell have you
people been smoking out there?
They're just
goddamn trees!
(LAUGHING)
You need to wake up,
Parker.
No. You need to wake up.
The wealth of this world isn't in the ground.
It's all around us.
The Na'vi know that, and they
are fighting to defend it.
If you want to share
this world with them,
you need to
understand them.
I'd say we understand them just
fine, thanks to Jake here.
Hey, Doc,
come take a look.
They're not gonna
give up their home.
make a deal.
(SCOFFING) For what?
Lite beer?
And blue jeans?
There's nothing that we
have that they want.
Everything they sent me out
here to do is a waste of time.
They're never gonna
leave Hometree.
So,
since a deal can't be made, I
guess things get real simple.
Jake, thanks.
I'm getting all emotional I might
just give you a big wet kiss.
(SIGHS)
(ULULATING)
(EXCLAIMING)
(SCREECHING)
QUARITCH :
Talk to me, Lyle.
It looks like they hit it
with banshees first.
See the angle's steep?
They set the ampsuit
on fire.
Driver's toast.
The rest of the squad?
Six bodies.
That's all of them.
The equipment's totaled.
Jesus Christ.
I'll do it with minimal
casualties to the indigenous.
I'll drive them out
with gas first.
(SIGHS)
It'll be humane.
More or less.
All right,
let's pull the trigger.
MAX : Come on, people.
Let's get it packed, let's go.
You know, they never even
wanted us to succeed.
They bulldozed a sacred site on
purpose to trigger a response.
Just fabricating this war
to get what they want.
This is how it's done.
When people are sitting
on shit that you want,
you make them
your enemy.
Then you're justified
in taking it.
Quaritch is rolling the gunships.
He's gonna hit Hometree.
My God.
Dr. Augustine!
You cannot be up here!
Back off!
Parker. Wait. Stop.
These are people you're about to...
No. No, no, no, no.
I said back off!
They're fly-bitten savages
that live in a tree!
All right?
Look around!
I don't know about you, but I see
a lot of trees! They can move!
Can you guys just please...
Yes, sir.
There are families in there.
There are children. Babies.
Are you gonna
kill children?
You don't want that kind of blood
on your hands. Believe me.
Just let me try
to talk them out.
They trust me.
Calibrate fast.
We're going in, right now.
FEMALE TECHNICIAN :
Calibrating three and four.
GRACE : Run sequence.
MAX : Initiating.
Thirty seconds.
(POWERING UP)
Listen to me.
You've got one hour.
Unless you want your girlfriend
in there when the ax comes down,
you get them to evacuate.
One hour.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Listen!
Speak, Jakesully.
A great evil is upon us...
The Sky People are coming"
...to destroy Hometree.
Look, tell them they're
gonna be here soon.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
(IN ENGLISH) You have to
leave, or you're gonna die.
Are you
certain of this?
Look, they sent me here
to learn your ways
so one day I could bring this message
and that you would believe it.
NEYTIRI : What are you saying, Jake?
You knew this would happen?
Yes.
JAKE : Look, at first
it was just orders,
and then
everything changed.
Okay? I fell in love.
I fell in love with the forest
and with the Omaticaya people.
And with you.
NEYTIRI : I trusted you.
With you. With you.
I trusted you!
Trust me now, please.
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
You will never be
one of The People!
I shouldn't have...
We tried to stop them!
Neytiri, please!
Please.
(MO'AT SPEAKING NA'VI)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Bind them.
(GRACE SPEAKING NA'VI)
Leave now!
You have to go.
They're coming!
(SHOUTING WAR CRY)
(ALL SHOUTING WAR CRY)
DRAGON PILOT : Time on
target, one mike.
SCORPION PILOT :
Copy. We have a visual.
Roger that.
Stay on heading 030.
SCORPION PILOT :
Roger, 030.
(BOTH SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
Run to the forest!
They're coming!
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
They will destroy
this place.
Neytiri,
you must go now!
(YIPPING)
Run to the forest!
Run!
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
Run! Run!
Have no Fear"
No! God damn it, run!
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
...attack from above.
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
That is one
big damn tree.
Well, well, well.
I'd say diplomacy has failed.
I want every gas round you
got right in the front door.
Roger.
CS.40's going hot.
Fire.
Firing.
(ALL SCREAMING)
(ALL COUGHING)
Bingo. Mighty good shooting, ace.
(SCREAMING IN NA'VI)
Sir, they've
opened fire.
(ARROWS CLATTERING)
QUARITCH : You've got to
be kidding me!
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
(ALL COUGHING)
These dumb bastards
ain't getting the message.
All right,
let's turn up the heat.
Switch incendiaries!
Switching incendiaries.
Fire.
No!
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
Get everyone to the Forest.
And that's how
you scatter the roaches.
(EYTUKAN SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
JAKE; Neytiri!
We gotta move!
He's gonna blow the columns!
My God!
(COMMANDING IN NA'VI)
(PROTESTING)
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
Mo'at! No!
If you are one of us,
help us.
All call signs,
switch missiles.
Give me HE 's at the base
of the west columns.
This Way!
OFFICER ON RADIO : Rider
section, switch missiles.
PILOT #1 : One's good.
PILOT #2 : Two's rocks up.
PILOT #3 : Three's up.
Yeah, baby, get some!
Charlie Oscar,
Gunrunner standing by.
Bring it down.
Cleared hot.
(ALL GRUNTING)
Come on,
Grace, move!
Down! Head down!
Come on,
come on! Down!
(GROANING)
PILOT #1 : Solid hits.
PILOT #2 : Solid rocks on target.
Screw this.
Hey! What the hell
are you doing?
I didn't sign up
for this shit!
OFFICER : Repeat.
Ripple fire.
(WOOD CREAKING)
Go! Go! Go!
(VILLAGERS SCREAMING)
(YIPPING)
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
(SCREECHING)
No, no, get back! Back!
(YELLS)
(EXCLAIMING IN PANIC)
(ALL SCREAMING)
Come on! Come on, move! Move!
(VILLAGERS SCREAMING)
(SCREAMING IN HORROR)
That's good work, people.
First round's on me tonight.
Let's boogie.
PILOT : Dragon coming
left, heading home.
OFFICER :
Gunrunner coming left.
Thunder copies.
Rider section copies.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Father I
(MOANING)
(WAILING IN NA'VI)
(GROANING WEAKLY)
Daughter...
(SOBBING)
Protect The People.
Neytiri!
(SOBBING)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
(WAILING IN GRIEF)
I'm sorry.
(SOBBING) Get away.
(SHRIEKING) Get away!
Get away from here!
Never come back!
(WAILING)
Pull the plug.
No, you can't do that!
WOMAN : You can't do that!
Calm down! Calm down!
No! Please!
(GIRL SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
JAKE : I was a warrior who
dreamed he could bring peace.
(ALL ARGUING)
Sooner or later, though,
you always have to wake up.
(DISTANTLY) Let's go!
Put him down!
You murderer!
(VILLAGERS SOBBING)
What's going on, brother?
Long time no see.
SECURITY MAN : Hey.
Personally, I don't feel these
tree-hugging traitors deserve steak.
They get steak? That's bullshit.
Let me see that.
(CHUCKUNG)
Yeah. You know
what that is. Down.
Trudy!
All the way down.
(GROANS)
Max!
Trudy, fire up
the ship! Go!
Here.
Clear. Come on.
Here you go.
Max, stay here.
I need someone on the inside I can trust.
Okay. Go.
NORM : (SOFTLY) Clear.
(ENGINE POWERING UP)
Come on, baby.
Colonel? Sir?
I got a situation here.
It's Samson 1-6.
Unauthorized engine start.
NORM : (GRUNTING) Three!
Come on!
Mask on!
Gas, gas, gas!
I'm taking fire!
Let's go!
Grab my hand!
Come on, we're in. Let's go!
Come on, let's go!
Let's go, go!
Colonel!
(AIR HISSING)
Yeah! Yeah!
NORM : All right! Yes!
(LAUGHS)
(WHOOPING)
Crap.
TRUDY : Everybody
all right back there?
JAKE : Oh, yeah, baby!
Now, you good?
NORM : Yeah!
(GROANING) This is gonna
ruin my whole day.
Grace is hit!
What?
Get the trauma kit.
Trauma kit!
Keep the pressure on,
Grace.
Trauma kit's forward,
on the bulkhead.
Hang on, Grace.
Doesn't matter.
It's fine.
(STIFLES GROAN)
JAKE ON RADIO :
You're good to go.
Take it up!
TRUDY ON RADIO : Hold on.
I'm pulling pitch.
You're clear!
Just keep going north.
Get us deep in the mountains.
TRUDY : Copy that.
Norm, you all
good up there?
Yep! Still here.
Well, at least they can't track us up here.
Not this far into the Vortex.
It's strongest at the
Tree of Souls, right?
Yeah.
Good. 'Cause that's
where we're going.
Ouch.
You big baby.
We're moving.
I'm gonna get you
some help, Grace.
I'm a scientist,
remember?
I don't believe
in fairy tales.
The People
can help you.
I know it.
Why would
they help us?
JAKE : The People say
Eywa will provide.
With no home,
no hope,
there was only
one place they could go.
(SOBBING)
Link's running.
What's the plan
here, Jake?
There's no plan.
Tsu'tey is Olo'eyktan now.
He's not gonna let you near that place.
I gotta try...
Launching.
(EXHALES)
(COUGHING)
JAKE : Outcast.
Betrayer.
Alien.
I was in the place
the eye does not see.
I needed their help,
and they needed mine.
But to ever
face them again,
I was gonna have to take
it to a whole new level.
(SCREECHING)
Sometimes your whole life
boils down to one insane move.
There's something
we gotta do.
You're not
gonna like it.
Yah!
(SQUAWKING)
The way I had it figured, Toruk
is the baddest cat in the sky.
Nothing attacks him.
Easy, boy...
So why would
he ever look up?
But that was
just a theory.
(GRUNTING)
(ROAR/NG)
(ALL SINGING IN NA'VI)
(ALL MURMURING
IN GROWING ALARM)
(SCREAMING)
(ALL SCREAMING)
(ROARING)
Toruk Macto?
(GROWLING SOFTLY)
(VILLAGERS MURMURING)
(PANTING SOFTLY)
I See you.
I was afraid, Jake.
For my people.
I'm not any more.
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
Tsu'tey son of Atsyo...
...I stand before you...
...ready to serve the Omaticaga People.
You are Olo'eyktan, and
you are a great warrior.
I can't do this
without you.
(ROARING)
Toruk Macto,
I will fly with you.
My friend is dying.
Grace is dying.
I beg the help
of Eyvva.
(ALL CHANTING)
Look where
we are, Grace.
I need to take
some samples.
(JAKE CHUCKLING SOFTLY)
The Great Mother may choose
to save all that she is
in this body.
Is that possible?
She must pass through the
eye of Eyvva and return.
But, Jakesully,
she is very weak.
Hang on, Grace.
They're gonna fix you up.
(MO'AT SPEAKING NA'VI)
Hear us Please, AH Mother.
Eyvva, Help her
Take this spirit into you...
(ALL REPLYING IN NA'VI)
...and breathe her back to us.
Lei: her' walk among us--
(ALL REPLYING IN NA'VI)
...as one of the People.
(ALL CHANTING)
(SPEAKS NA'VI)
(CHANTING STOPS)
(WEAKLY) Jake.
Grace.
I'm with her, Jake.
She's real!
(DISTANTLY) Grace?
Grace, please. Grace!
What's happening?
Grace!
JAKE : What's happening?
Did it work?
Her wounds were too great.
It was not enough time.
She is with Eyvva now.
With your permission,
I will speak now.
You would honor me
by translating.
The Sky People have
sent us a message
(TSU'TEY TRANSLATING)
that they can take
whatever they want
and no one
can stop them.
Well, we will send
them a message.
You ride out as fast as
the wind can carry you.
You tell the other
clans to come.
(EXCLAIMING IN AGREEMENT)
You tell them Toruk
Macto calls to them.
And you fly now
with me!
My brothers!
Sisters!
(ALL HOOTING)
And we will show
the Sky People
that they cannot take
whatever they want,
and that this,
this is our land!
(REPEATING IN NA'VI)
(ALL CHEERING)
(ROARS) Yah!
(EXCLAIMING IN NA'VI)
Yah!
(SCREECHING)
(ALL CHATTERING EXCITEDLY)
(HOOTING)
Yah!
JAKE : We rode out
to the four winds.
(SHOUTS IN NA'VI)
To the horse clans
of the plain.
JAKE : Back to the stars!
To the ikran people
of the Eastern Sea.
For our children's
children!
When Toruk Macto called
them, they came.
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
(ALL CHEERING)
Yah!
(ULULATING)
(NEYTIRI HOOTING)
Everyone on this base,
every one of you,
is fighting
for survival.
That's a fact!
There's an aboriginal horde out
there massing for an attack.
Now, these orbital
images tell me
that the hostiles' numbers
have gone from a few hundred
to well over
2,000 in one day.
And more
are pouring in.
In a week's time, there
could be 20,000 of them.
At that point, they will
overrun our perimeter.
Well, that's not
gonna happen!
Our only security lies
in pre-emptive attack.
We will fight
terror with terror.
Now, the hostiles believe that
this mountain stronghold of theirs
is protected
by their...
(SCORNFULLY)
Their deity.
(SOLDIERS SNICKERING)
And when we destroy it,
we will blast a crater in
their racial memory so deep
that they won't come within 1,000
klicks of this place ever again.
And that, too,
mama.
(SOLDIERS CHEERING)
Yeah! Yeah.
(SOLDIERS CHATTERING)
Jake, it's crazy here.
It's full mobilization.
They're rigging the
shuttle as a bomber.
It's for some kind of
shock-and-awe campaign.
Fricking daisy cutters!
Quaritch has taken over.
He's rolling, and there's no stopping him.
When?
0600 tomorrow.
WOMAN : Max! Max!
I gotta go.
We're screwed!
(TRUDY LAUGHING)
And I was hoping for some
sort of tactical plan
that didn't involve
martyrdom.
TRUDY : We're going up against
gunships with bows and arrows.
I have 15 clans
out there.
That's over
2,000 warriors.
Now, we know
these mountains.
We fly them. You fly them.
They don't.
Their instruments
won't work up here.
Missile tracking
won't work.
They'll have to fire
a line of sight.
If they bring
the fight to us,
then we have the
home-field advantage.
You know he's gonna
commit that bomber
straight to
the Tree of Souls.
Yeah, I know.
If they get to the Tree
of Souls, it's over.
That's their direct line
to Eyvva, their ancestors.
It'll destroy them.
Then I guess we'd
better stop him.
(EXHALES SOFTLY)
I'm probably just talking
to a tree right now.
(SIGHS)
But if you're there, I need
to give you a heads-up.
If Grace is with you,
look into her memories.
See the world
we come from.
There's no green there.
They killed
their Mother.
And they're gonna do
the same here.
More Sky People
are gonna come.
They're gonna come like
a rain that never ends.
Unless we stop them.
Look, you chose me
for something.
I will stand
and fight.
You know I will.
Butlneed
a little help here
Our Great Mother does
not take sides, Jake.
(SIGHS)
She protects only
the balance of life.
It was worth a try.
(BOTH SIGHING)
MAN : Yeah! Yeah!
That's what I'm talking about!
Yeah! Yeah! That's what
I'm talking about, man!
This is Group Leader.
We are entering the Flux Vortex.
Switch to manual
flight mode.
PILOT : Copy.
Manual flight mode.
This is Papa Dragon.
I want this mission
high and tight.
I want to be
home for dinner.
Suit Team, go.
All right, ladies,
let's bring the pain!
STAFF SERGEANT :
Move, move, move!
AMPSUIT COMMANDER #1 :
Bravo 1-1, move left.
AMPSUIT COMMANDER #2 : Bravo 1-1 moving left.
Watch flank.
Watch formation.
Keep moving.
Charlie 2- 1,
watch your spacing.
AMPSUIT COMMANDER #1 :
Copy that. Over.
Eyes up. Check that overhead.
And watch those thermal scans.
All call signs, Papa has
lead, pushing to target.
Escorts, stay close
on my shuttle.
We are gonna lose
some paint in here.
QUARITCH : Gun crews,
keep your head on a swivel.
Make no mistake, people,
they're out there.
All right, people, target in sight.
Range, four klicks.
Valkyrie 1-6,
get your payload ready.
Copy.
Prepare to offload.
Staff Sergeant,
stage the weapon.
Roll it to the ramp!
Let's go!
Hold!
AMPSUIT COMMANDER #2 : Charlie
2- 1, got big movement.
Hold position.
Hold up, hold up.
We got movement out
there, 500 meters.
Charlie 2- 1,
hold position.
Sir, ground has movement!
Fast approaching.
PILOT : Charlie Oscar,
Rider section.
Firing line!
Targets closing.
Range, 400 meters.
Can't you clean it up?
No, sir.
It's the Flux.
(SHOUTING)
(WHOOPING)
(WARRIORS HOOTING)
(SCREAMING)
(SCREECHING)
(HOOTING)
(SHOUTING IN NA'VI)
(ULULATING)
(WHOOPING)
Brother, I'm gonna
punch a hole.
You follow me through.
(RESPONDS IN NA'VI)
(ALL ULULATING)
(APPROACHING WAR CRIES)
(SCREECHING)
(SCREAMING)
(EXCLAIMING)
(EXCLAIMS)
All aircraft, weapons free!
Weapons free!
Break right.
Come around.
Light them up!
Break formation,
engage all hostiles.
Yeah! Get some!
(SCREAMING)
Scorpions,
pursue and destroy.
Jake!Jake!
You copy?
We're falling back!
We're getting hammered!
Copy.
Get out of there.
(SCREECHING)
That's him.
Get after him!
Take him out!
Oops.
Light her up!
Right there!
You're not the only one
with a gun, bitch.
Keep her in your sights.
Purging. Feeding the leak.
Arming all pods.
That's it!
(GASPS)
(SHRIEKS)
(GRUNTING)
Seyzey!
(GASPING IN CONCERN)
(SHRIEKS)
(SCREAMS)
(SHOUTING)
TRUDY : Rogue One is hit.
I'm going in.
Sorry, Jake.
(GRUNTS)
Fire.
(PANTING)
Tsu'tey! Brother,
do you read?
Rogue One,
you copy?
Trudy!
(GASPING)
Time to target,
two minutes.
Valkyrie 1-6, you are
cleared and hot.
Copy, Dragon.
We are starting our bomb run.
Arm number one!
Number one armed!
Ma Jake!
I read you.
JAKE.' Neytiri!
Seyzey's dead.
They are very close.
They are many.
Do not attack.
Do you read me,
Neytiri?
Do not attack!
Fall back now. Get out of there!
That's an order!
Neytiri!
AMPSUIT COMMANDER #2 : I got
movement, I got movement.
Hold position.
Something's coming.
AMPSUIT COMMANDER #1 : Bravo 1-1, I got
a big seating. Turn screens over.
We got movement
200 meters.
Hold your formation.
Be ready.
Watch your flanks.
Hundred meters
and closing fast.
(TRUMPETING)
(EXCLAIMING)
We gotta get
out of here!
Fall back! Fall back!
AMPSUIT COMMANDER #1 :
Move! Move! Move!
Fall back!
On the run! On the run!
(SCREAMING)
Jake, Eyvva
has heard you.
(SCREECHING)
Eyvva has heard you!
(ALL SCREECHING)
Come on!
(SNARLING)
Fall back!
Move! Move!
(SCREAMING)
(EXCLAIMS)
(ROARING)
(ROARS)
(EXHALES SLOWLY)
PILOT : Sir!
All escorts are down or falling back.
Let's get this done.
Valkyrie 1-6, this is Dragon.
Press to target.
Copy.
Pressing to target.
Stand by to drop,
30 seconds.
(SHOUTING)
On my mark.
Two, one, mark.
Drop! Drop! Drop!
Go, go, go, go!
(SCREAMING)
QUARITCH : Brace!
QUARITCH : It's Sully.
(ALARM BLARING)
Mask on!
Breach alarm!
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTS)
(ROARING)
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
Come on.
Come to papa.
(NEYTIRI SCREAMING)
(HOWLING IN PAIN)
(SHRIEKS)
(GRUNTING)
(NEYTIRI GROANING)
(HISSING)
JAKE : Give it up,
Quaritch!
It's all over.
QUARITCH : Nothing's over
while I'm breathing.
JAKE : I kind of hoped
you'd say that.
(GRUNTING)
(ROARING)
(GASPING)
(GRUNTING)
(ALARM BEEPING)
Come on!
(GASPS)
QUARITCH : Hey, Sully, how's it feel
to betray your own race?
(HISSING)
You think you're one of them?
Time to wake up.
(ALARM BLARING)
(JAKE GRUNTING)
(GRUNTING)
(ALARM BLARING)
(COUGHING)
(GASPING)
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
(PANTING)
(GROANS)
(GASPING)
(EXCLAIMS)
(GRUNTS)
(HISSING)
Jake?
(GASPING)
(GRUNTING)
(GASPS)
Jake.
(PANTING SHALLOWLY)
(GASPS)
(EXHALES)
(MOANING)
NEYTIRI : Jake! Ma Jake!
(AIR HISSING FAINTLY)
(COUGHING)
(PRESSURIZING)
(BREATHING DEEPLY)
I See you.
(EXCLAIMING)
(GASPING)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
I See you, Brother.
Are The People safe?
They're safe.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
I can't...
I cannot lead
The People.
You must lead them...
Jakesully.
I'm not officer material.
It is decided.
Now...
...do the duty
of Olo'eyktan.
I will not kill you
It is the way!
And it is good.
I will be remembered.
I fought...with
Toruk Macto!
And we were brothers.
And he...was
my last shadow.
(GASPS)
(GROANS)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)
JAKE : The aliens went back
to their dying world.
Only a few
were chosen to stay.
The time of great sorrow
was ending.
Toruk Macto was
no longer needed.
(SCREECHING)
Well, I guess this is
my last video log.
'Cause whatever happens
tonight, either way, I'm...
I'm not gonna be coming
back to this place.
Well, I guess
I'd better go.
Yeah, I don't want to be
late for my own party.
(CHUCKLES)
Yeah, it's my birthday,
after all.
This is Jake Sully
signing off.
(ALL CHANTING)
(SPEAKING NA'VI)